Guide to the Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies (Hartford and Connecticut Chapters) Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies (Hartford and Connecticut Chapters) papers
1939-1944
MS 66
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, speeches, writings, subject files, printed matter, and clippings of the Hartford and Connecticut chapters of the CDAAA, an anti-isolationist organization formed for the purpose of influencing public opinion and lobbying in favor of U.S. assistance to the Allied powers. The principal figures of this organization represented in the collection are Walter E. Batterson, Eleanor Taft Tilton, and H. M. Dadourian. There is also material relating to John Danaher and the Danaher-McMahon senatorial contest (Connecticut, 1944).
Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies. Hartford and Connecticut Chapters
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter E. Batterson, 1952, and Eleanor Taft Tilton, 1958.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Speeches and Writings. III. Subject File. IV. Printed Matter.
Scope and Contents
These papers encompass the activities of the Hartford and Connecticut chapters of the CDAAA between 1940 and 1941 (mostly 1941). Materials pertaining to this organization comprises two-thirds of the collection; the other third consists of materials relating to John Danaher and the Danaher McMahon senatorial contest (Connecticut 1944). The principals of the collection are Walter E. Batterson and Mrs. Arthur V.R. Tilton (Eleanor Taft). In addition there is some correspondence of H.M. Dadourian and material relating to other organizations of the early and mid-forties.
The papers are divided into four series: Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject Files, and Printed Matter.
The National Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies was organized in May, 1940 for the purpose of influencing public opinion and lobbying in favor of United States assistance to the allied powers. William Allen White, an influential Kansas editor, and Clark Mell Eichelberger were prime movers in organizing the CDAAA and served respectively as national chairman. White resigned January 4, 1941. Hence, most of the material pertaining to the national organization in this collection involves Clark Eichelberger. The national CDAAA was prointervention, lobbied in favor of the Lend-Lease Bill, recognition of DeGaulle's government in exile, against the neutrality act, and against the propaganda of the America First group. The national organization is chiefly represented in this collection through correspondence and published material in the "Printed Matter" series.
The Hartford chapter of the CDAAA was organized soon after the national headquarters was established and followed the general national policy. The chairman of the Hartford chapter was Walter E. Batterson a former mayor of that city. With the emergence of a state organization he served similtaneously as the chairman of the Connecticut and Hartford chapters. Batterson retained these two positions until October, 1941 when the state CDAAA merged with an organization of similar purpose, Fight for Freedom Inc. He then served as a co-chairman of the new organization, Fight for Freedom Committee to Defend America, while H. M. Dadourian headed the Hartford organization. The activities of the committees stopped shortly after the bombing of Pearl Harbor.
Eleanor Taft Tilton was active in both the state and local CDAAA. She served as a vice-chairman of the Hartford chapter and as a member of the state committee-at-large. She was also secretary of Americans United for World Organization in the mid-forties and worked in opposition to the reelection of John Danaher in 1944.
John Danaher, Republican Senator from Connecticut 1939-1945 is the subject of a portion of the material in this collection. Danaher's votes against such acts as the Naval Appropriations Bill, the Selective Service Act and the Lend-Lease Bill made him one of the chief congressional opponents of the program that the CDAAA wanted to promote. The CDAAA opposed Danaher's opinions through meetings, press statements, and letters to the editor. Material related to the anti-Danaher campaign is present in each series of the collection, but is primarily found in "Speeches and Writings", "Subject Files", and "Printed Matter."
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1940 for the purpose of influencing public opinion and lobbying in favor of U.S. assistance to the Allies; organized by William Allen White and Clark Mell Eichelberger; Hartford chapter chairman was Walter E. Batterson; in 1941 merged with Fight for Freedom, Inc., to form the Fight for Freedom Committee to Defend America.
Intervention (International law); Neutrality; World War, 1939-1945; Connecticut -- Politics and government; Connecticut; United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- Politics and government; Batterson, Walter E.; Bell, Ulric, 1891-1960; Dadourian, H. M. (Haroutune Mugurditch), 1878-1974; Danaher, John Anthony, 1899-; Eichelberger, Clark M. (Clark Mell), 1896-1980; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974; Maloney, Francis Thomas, 1894-1945; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; Tilton, Eleanor Taft, 1909-1984; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944; Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies. Hartford and Connecticut Chapters
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1940-1944; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is divided into four subsections: the first three subsections consist of the correspondence of the principals of the collection—Walter E. Batterson, H. M. Dadourian, and Eleanor T. Tilton; the last section consists of correspondence of others. Within each subsection the correspondence is arranged alphabetically. The first and largest subsection is the correspondence of Walter E. Batterson (1940-1941). Batterson corresponded with most of Connecticut's congressional representatives and officials of pro and anti-intervention groups. His correspondence also includes letters with CDAAA national headquarters and letters to the editors of various publications.
  The second subsection, the correspondence of H. M. Dadourian, and the third subsection, the correspondence of Eleanor Taft Tilton, are smimilar in content to the Batterson correspondence, but smaller. Mrs. Tilton's correspondence includes some letters relating to the Danaher-McMahon contest for the Senate in 1944.
  - Walter E. Batterson
    - General Correspondence A-C (34), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bell, Ulric (10), 1941 October 3-November 8, 1944 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Conant, James B.& Lewis W. Douglas (6), 1940 December 24-1941 January (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Congressional Correspondence (28), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Congressional Correspondence re: questionnaire (8), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence D-H, (28), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dadourian, H. M., Chairman (1), 1941 June 27 & August 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Danaher, John A. (10), 1940 September 4-1941 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - DeGaulle, Charles telegram (1), 1941 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Eichelberger, Clark M. (30), 1940 December 7-1941 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Form letters (6), 1941 May 10,1943 December 14, 1944 January 3 undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hoover, John Edgar (3), 1941 June 16-October 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence I-R (24), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Koppleman, Herman P. (10), 1940 November 19-1941 December (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters to the Editor (14), 1940 June 7 -1941,October 22, n.d (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Maloney, Francis T. (17), 1940 July 26-1941 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Robinson, David (5), 1940 December 11-1941 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (9), 1941 May 27-1941 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - General Correspondence s-z (26), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Seymour, Charles (4), 1941 October 24-November 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Sherman, Maurice (8), 1941 May 31 - October 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Stinger Gilbert (3), 1941 February (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Thomas, Mrs. Harrison A. (5), 1940 September 17 - 1941 November 12 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Tilton, Mrs. Arthur (3), 1941 June 27 & December 10, 1943 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Wilkie, Wendell L. (10), 1941 May 8 - October 27 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dadourian, H.M.
    - Bell, Ulric (3), 1941 November (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Bissill, William T. (1), 1941 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Eichelberger, Clark M. (4), 1941 November 25 - December (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Lindbergh, Charles A. (1), 1941 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Congressional Correspondence, (6), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Letters to the editor, (3), 1941 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Tilton, Mrs. Arthur (Eleanor Taft Tilton)
    - General Correspondence A-Z, (30), 1940-1941, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Congressional Correspondence A-Z, (7), 1941, 1943, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Letters to the editor (19), 1941 March 6 - November 12, n.d (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Van Dusen, Henry P. (5), 1941 April 1 - May 20 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence of others
    - General, (10), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Letters to the editor, (9), 1940-1941 August (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Letters to the editor, (14), 1941 September - December, 1943 July 12, December 6, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1941-1944; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  SPEECHES AND WRITINGS consists of the writings and speeches of CDAAA members, including the speeches of Walter Batterson; drafts, notes, and an interview by Eleanor Taft Tilton; and speeches by others given under the auspicies of the CDAAA.
  - Batterson, Walter E.:, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Connecticut Conference of Youth (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Newtown Rally (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Hartford, Ickes Rally (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Rotary Club, Kiwanis, YMCA (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Russian-Ukrainian Rally (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - WTIC Debate Memorial Day (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Meridan, 4th of July, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Batterson, Walter E.: untitled, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Overstreet, Alan Burr--Radio talk for Americans United for World Organization, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Seymour, Charles, President of Yale University, "Aid for the Allies" (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Sherwood, Robert E., author, anti-Lindbergh speech, clipping (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Tilton, Mrs. Arthur V., interviews, speeches (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Tilton, Mrs. Arthur V., notes, drafts, articles, etc. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Writings of others: John L. Simson, unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
- SUBJECT FILES, 1939-1944; Series III
  SUBJECT FILES contains a variety of materials including minutes of meetings, membership lists, resolutions, statements, press releases, and other materials relating to the CDAAA. In addition, there are materials pertaining to the Ickes Rally (includes correspondence), the Continental Congress for Freedom, and a compilation of Senator John Danaher's public statements and voting record which was compiled by the CDAAA for use against Danaher in the senatorial campaign of 1944.
  - America First Committee: advertisements, clippings, miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Americans United for World Organization, National and Connecticut Chapters (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Anti-intervention press: photographs, etc. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Associated Leagues for a Declared War: propaganda leaflets (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - CDAAA
    - Hartford Chapter: minutes of Executive Committee meetings, 1941 April 22 - December 9 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Hartford Chapter, Trade Union Division: committee membership list, statement of principles, petition (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Hartford and Connecticut Chapters: list of committee membership (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Hartford and Connecticut Chapters: miscellaneous lists (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Hartford and Connecticut Chapters: resolutions and statement of objectives (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Hartford and Connecticut Chapters: press releases, 1940 December 12 - 1941 October 30 undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Hartford and Connecticut Chapters: misc. and letterheads (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - National Headquarters, Hartford and Connecticut Chapters: policy statements (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - National Headquarters: press releases with clippings, etc. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - State Chapters: resolutions and fund raising emblems (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Survey and lists of pro-CDAAA and pro-America First letters to editors (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Connecticut 5th Congressional District of Democratic and Republican town chairmen, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Continental Congress for Freedom, District of Columbia: programs, resolutions, press release, and summary by Batterson, 1941 October 9-10 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Senator John A. Danaher
    - Excerpts from Congressional Record, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - "Legislation during the War Years," excerpts from the Congressional Record, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "Vermin Press," "Subversive Press" excerpts from anti-interventionists and press, 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "Anti-Semitic and Anti-Alien," excerpts from The Malist Publication, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "Danaher Labor," excerpts from Congressional Record, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - "Carping Criticism," excerpts from Congressional Record, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - "Soldier Vote," excerpts from Congressional Record, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Voting records and statements, 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - John Danager-McMahon campaign: press releases, statements, clippings, campaign advertisement (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Fight for Freedom Committee: history, publicity, newsletter, miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Fight for Freedom Committee to Defend America: list of officers, objectives (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Ickes Rally, Hartford: correspondence, Ickes speech, statements, publicity, miscellaneous, 1941 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 75)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1941; Series IV; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  PRINTED MATTER is divided into three subsections:
  (1) Publications of CDAAA, including the "Headquarters Letter" by Clark Eichelberger; the "Progress Bulletin" containing news from local chapters; and the "Washington Office Information Letter," which covers Capital Hill activities. (2) Newspaper clippings grouped by subject, for example, Senator John Danaher, or clippings by an author, for example, George Gallup's public opinion surveys. (3) General newspaper clippings, consisting of a scrapbook of clippings collected in 1941, primarily from Hartford newspapers.
  In addition, there are some miscellaneous pamphlets at the end of the series.
  - CDAA
    - National headquarters--"Headquarters Letter" Nos. 1-11, 13-15, 1941 August-December (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - National headquarters--"Progress Bulletin," Nos. 16-17, 23-29, 1941 January-August (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Washington Office--"Information Letter," Nos. 5-6, 8, 10-14, 16,17, 19-40, 42-47, 1941 February-December (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Newspaper Clippings(by subject or author)
    - Dorothy Thompson, editorials, 1941 September-October (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - George Gallup, public opinion surveys, 1941 June-December (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - John Danaher (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Charles Lindbergh (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Presidential speeches--text of address by Herbert Hoover and texts of speeches by F.D. Roosevelt, 1941 September-December (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Pro-intervention political cartoons, Circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - CDAAA: advertisements and political cartoons, Circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Miscellaneous re: CDAAA (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Re: foreign policy (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Newspaper Clippings(general)
    - Hartford Times, 1941 April 28 - December 10 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Editorials Hartford Times, 1941 June 16 - December 9 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Letters to editor Hartford Times, 1941 May-December (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Hartford Courant, 1941 May 8 - December 13 (Box 3, Folder 91-92)
    - Hartford Courant, 1941 May 13 - December 11 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Editorials Hartford Courant, 1941 May 5 - December 11 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - New York City papers, 1941 May 10 - December 9, undated (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Hartford Courant, 1941 May 11 - November 21 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Hartford Times, 1941 May 5 - November 17 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Miscellaneous fragments (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Miscellaneous published matter, speeches and pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Miscellaneous published matter (Box 4, Folder 99)